welcome Jay cousins to project raising
and he'll be talking about his project
all of being home and get away Jay yeah
thanks very much the opportunity Jubilee
so the I'm presently the the default
patterns by which we live almost
everything that we do is environmentally
and socially destructive almost by
default and this is obviously hugely
problematic when we scale this across
the number of billions of us that there
are on the planet so to take a case in
point like I mean I mean a house in
dahab at the moment and during the
during the summer time because the
buildings built of concrete it takes a
huge amount of energy to keep the
building cool because I need to use
air-conditioning in order to maintain
thermal comfort now it's wintertime I
have the polar opposite of the problem
it's an enormously costly to heat and I
can't maintain thermal comfort again
because of the way that the building is
designed but we can essentially
extrapolate this across almost every
aspect of our lives and down to our
diets if we are eating bread for example
there cornfields from the perspective of
butterflies birds and numerous insects
is essentially a uncrossable as it so
we're destroying habitats pattern that
we so the attempt is really to look at
in order that homes and houses habitat
generating rather than habitat
destroying and and how we actually
create systems for ourselves that we can
live in in a comfortable way but our
very existence is contributing to the
creation of habitat to the creation of
food and to build a better environment
for ourselves and also society and other
beings on the planet that we
a planet with that provide us with the
essential services that we need how I'm
approaching that and and trying to
approach that is to explore how we
presently take our wastes because I've
been coming at it from a position of not
having a lot of resource and not having
a lot of access to money and funds which
I found myself over the last year or so
so I began experimenting with trash that
I found on the streets of dahab so
there's a lot of plastic waste here
which is a huge problem and there's also
a lot of palm fronds and palm wastes
that can be found in the environment and
I started to take that and transform it
to create structures to begin with
things like furniture tables chairs and
things like that and that allow me to
provide for my immediate needs but now
I'm exploring it on a larger scale
making things like and this is in the
early stages but start to make dome and
yes and tents and I hope to make
stronger more durable structures
ultimately that can grow habitat on the
outside and can provide the vault
dweller on-site the core of what I'm
doing and and what I'm developing but
I'm also exploring it from the
perspective of it these challenges and
these problems they can't be solved on
like by by one set of mind and and hands
and heart working on it
I need many other people also
considering these challenges considering
how you can actually build and and
create an alternative existence for
ourselves so this has been more of a
kind of long-term quest over the last
few years there's been this question how
do we move from a culture that's
predominantly oriented around
when we make anything it's in the
digital sphere and there's a lot of
computers in a way of our production and
our thinking about things and how we
produce things and how do we get more
people engaging with the world with
their hands with reality with their
hands in order that they can better
understand how to engage with reality
and how to make things so on that scale
of things I have a game called context
craft this is just with beeswax and
sticks that allows for the making of
three-dimensional geometries but
anything that's made using the sticks
and beeswax can be replicated using
plastic bottles and sticks or even
cardboard if it's appropriately treated
in order to make large-scale structures
so whatever you design through play and
through the game you can actually go on
and make big so that's essentially the
core of where I'm at and what I'm about
that present there's been a number of
spin-off products that have come out of
it which is one of the challenges and
issues that I have as as an inventor is
I keep coming up with products and I
need assistance in getting these
products out into the world that people
can access them and use them but I've
been down the entrepreneurial path in
the past and it's led me down into a
kind of management rabbit hole I
understood their marketing and the sales
I built up international networks of
distribution with my previous company
but it just doesn't interest me and it
takes me away from what I'm good at
which is actually coming up with new
designs new ideas and new solutions and
and taking this kind of approach so I
mean my core things that I'm looking to
achieve I guess over the next hour is
one is to just have the opportunity to
express what I'm up to and and what I've
been doing over the last year and get
some feedback on how clear it is what
I'm doing what I'm about whether
the message is really muddied or whether
it's clear communication of what I'm
actually doing and also find others that
can that are interested to actually
start exploring some of these challenges
that we have in order to find their own
solutions discover and share their own
solutions or perhaps copy some of the
the ideas and the learning that I've
been able to develop over the last year
or so thank you sorry can someone else
yeah I can I can continue on so J thanks
for that it sounds like a good idea that
the world can use and ROI value from so
that's that's awesome I think your
initial description I I think I
understood what you were doing so
there's not a problem with like oh what
what's this guy up to afterwards which a
lot of pitches have that initially so so
that's good
I think there's I think there's a room
for improvement as far as clarity and
getting specific and of course it sounds
like you also could use a little bit of
focus yourself I mean it sounds like you
got a lot of options to go down and of
course you're only one person right so
far
so let me so I don't know if if Ed Rio
if you had anything you want any
questions about what he said or if you
want to add anything and then other than
that we can I can jump into the
aspirations and sure yeah I'm just
trying to understand I guess the
separation but between what I understood
was the eventual goal of the overall
thing which sounded like it was
improving on efficient design
specifically or also to do with things
generating habitats and then how that
compares to what it sounded like the
products like the stakes in the beeswax
to to build structures and sort
how those two work together or coincide
you know yeah so thanks for the
opportunity to clarify on that so
essentially what the the beeswax and
sticks is is allowing people to do is to
start to explore geometry and understand
how material structures can be created
through geometry so if you look at
things like butt Minster Fuller and what
he achieved with the the geodesic domes
and various other forms that he was
discovering and exploring a lot of that
learning comes from geometric play and
tactile play and haptic play and this is
something that we're not really teaching
in schools so much nowadays so a lot of
the schools are leaning more towards
digital production at least from what
I've observed and also I ran a
makerspace in in Berlin I co-founded
some years ago and again there was a
very strong leaning and a very strong
drawer towards things like MakerBot's 3d
printers laser cutters CNCs
and things of that nature but what they
need to is a complexity of construction
so when when people start to think about
how they solve problems and how they
solve for problems instead of looking at
the the materials lying around them and
how they might use those materials in
order to meet their needs what they do
is instead they they start to generally
design in in the space of CAD or to try
and find existing card things that's so
you're familiar with CAD computer-aided
design finding digital files and formats
that they can copy and produce and often
they get more kind of distracted and
locked into this space where they're
tinkering with the machines themselves
and trying to replicate the machines
whilst actually the machines are quite
limited in
their capacity to build because of the
surface areas that they're operating on
and so on and so forth but by playing
with the the beeswax and sticks on one
hand this is a replicatable game so
anybody can produce it anywhere in the
world you can order your own beeswax you
can order your own sticks you can
produce your own game very easily and
very effectively but also where it has
been played friends have observed for
example playing in Bedouin communities
in the South Sinai one of them was with
a architect student at the time and the
architect student was commenting that
what the kids were doing they didn't
learn until the fourth year of
architecture so there's there's a
structure through playing with the hands
and playing with physical geometry that
people come to understand what the the
physical properties are of a material in
order that they can understand how they
can then build larger structures at
scale and also also to give them the
what's the word I'm looking for the
belief that they can make things with
their hands and that they're capable of
making things with their hands because
there's also an issue with our material
confidence and our material competence
whenever we we look at things that other
people have produced or whether we
consider what we would be able to
produce so this is also a response to
some of the challenges that I've had
over the last few years and in
considering if I want to do a product
such as a geodesic dome that anybody can
produce or reproduce one of the
challenges I have to overcome is that
material literacy and the material
relationship with the world because a
lot of people just don't have that tool
so the game is kind of a
access point that gets people relating
to the world again with their hands
building up that set of knowledge and
what I call material literacy that you
can't necessarily learn in a book that
you can't necessarily even transfer over
a video you need that actual tactile
experience of the object and of the
material reality in order to understand
it and understand how to relate to it
and then once I've built up that
relationship through the game whatever
is whatever is designed and I'll point
you to the Instagram accounts and the
the images later or I can actually just
quickly I'll get you a larger shape it's
gonna be easier to understand so for
example this this dis larger form is a
basic structure that can hold weight
used as a structure for supporting
stools and things like that larger
versions of it have also been built to
when to suspend tables in a co-working
space and co-working hub and that thing
you just shared was that jazz bigger
steps bigger sticks and duct tape no
plastic bottles to make a weld and that
that weld is then heat shrunk around the
around the sticks these are palm
branches but you can also use it with
coppiced would for example depending on
your location or when we were in London
we I mean whilst there are trees in
London sticks are still hard to come by
but when you walk down the streets
everybody's throwing out
cardboard boxes from Amazon so I
discovered you can also shrink the
cardboard boxes you can make them into
rolls you can then shrink those rolls
into bottles and again you can make
sturdy
Strix stick structure that can then be
used to make scaffolding either for
domes or it could be structures that
vines can grow around because if we
increase the accessible surface area
outside of buildings for example using
these joining techniques then we can
create surfaces that shade and and
habitat can grow around so it's also
possible to explore how we might also
adapt the existing environments and
existing buildings that we're living in
using these techniques so for example
you could take a model of your house you
could play with it you could explore
using the wax and sticks what some
aesthetic geometries around the outside
could look like and then you could
actually create those structures and
create shade around the outside of your
house or better still grow shade grow
vertical gardens but I would recommend
vines rather than trying to plant trees
in the sky because vines are the best
vertical vertical farming methods that
we already have they produce shade they
produce crops and a lot of the
challenges that we're going to face
going forward are related to this this
problem of things getting too hot and
actually things can be if we put all of
our energy into pumping the heat away
from the buildings we're putting the
we're putting the thinking into the
challenge at the wrong stage the the the
challenge is actually just stopping the
Sun from hitting the building because if
it doesn't absorb the heat in the first
place then you don't have to put the
energy into getting it out so by
creating these these structures around
our existing buildings and our existing
dwellings and then growing habitat
growing plants
growing shade or creating shade through
other forms we can actually reduce a lot
of our energy costs and also create a
more comfortable environment as well as
potentially creating opportunities for
for crops and various other things so
does that make a bit more sense now as
to how these things have it how this
kind of wax wax geometry kind of plays
out and and scales to something larger I
think so if I understand you're saying
that the game sort of helps build like
the mental ability like the
understanding of you know what shapes
working don't and also you know people
how to work with the physical materials
as opposed to CAD which then you have to
you know how to get that into the real
world and that is moving towards sort of
a system where these structures it's it
sounds like at least for now wouldn't be
new buildings but rather things tacked
on to existing buildings to help achieve
this you know any more efficient did to
his I'm with helping with the the
thermal comfort as you called it but
then also providing a place for
creatures to live I mean the environment
I mean for example where I am in there's
a there's a there's a lot of land
available but there's a problem building
on that land due to government
regulation paperwork issues also family
access to money and various other things
so and they also have a lot of flat
rooftops which are again just catching
the heat of the Sun so where I am there
is also an opportunity for the creation
of kind of like and and dome-like
structures on the flat roof but in more
kind of I guess Western urban
environments then it's more likely to be
retrofit structures and exploring how
you can create more capacity for growth
on the outside of the existing
structures and existing dwellings so Jay
I wonder if you would wouldn't mind
giving me your kind of the initial
message again maybe like one or two
sentences because I want to tie that
back to what we've been talking about
the in essence is looking at how we can
how we can what is and and where we are
and to use that to grow shade and grow
food and increase the available habitat
for other beings other than humans alone
because there's also an issue that we
have like our cities are essentially
desert evolving and a lot of the issues
that we have with wildlife depletion
insect depletion and various other
things are as a direct result of of how
we relate to our overall environment and
how we relate to nature so to make this
kind of switch to turn our sterile
spaces into abundant spaces of of growth
and food shade and shelter okay so would
you say that that if you had like a
catch phrase for it it would be growing
growing chain food using what we have
today is my my general mantra that I'm
I'm applying because also when you look
at the the co2 in the atmosphere it's
essentially life in waiting all all all
life is made out of carbon there's a lot
of thinking about how we need to sink or
lock but again there's a kind of
engineering approaches to the the carbon
that we we have in the environment and
but what nature does is it turns that
carbon into life and that the more life
we create the more shade we create the
more habitat we create and these are
positive feedback loops that cool down
our cities they cool down our
environments and they can also produce
food as a by-product and as well as
reducing the carbon I mean basically
there's a lot required before we get
anywhere close to really addressing the
issue and it's not that we shouldn't
address the issue also at the source but
looking at what is and how we transform
it into something that's useful to us
and to everything else yeah I think the
keep common girl habitat is a good
phrase that would draw interest and then
something I would suggest go ahead and
crafting that that one sentence thing
when you've piqued people's interest to
kind of really simplify in their mind
something like grocery and food food
using what we have to benefit us and
animals and insects or you know however
you want to say that that other thing
and and then like you know other kind of
benefits after that like your sterile to
abundance for food and shade and shelter
which you you might be able to combine
those into one but I think it's great to
have in priority just a couple short
sentences to give people the boundaries
of your project because if it does
everything for everyone you can't fit
that in your brain but sounds like yeah
like you do have a good thing and then
unless you want more specific help on
that I would like to dive into some of
the challenges you were talking
about finding other people and you have
a lot of kind of product ideas that you
you don't want you're not interested in
being the person to bring them to market
but you feel there's a value and there
is there an a preference and where you'd
like to go in terms of where I would
like to go with it
aye-aye-aye my kind of drive isn't
monetary a tool and obviously yeah I
have certain needs I have a family to
take care of anything else but I'm I'm
lucky enough to be in a position of
privilege now this year whereby we
finally actually got some land and a
house for ourselves so it's it's not as
paramount as it as it once was
what I want to see is these these
products out in the wild I want to see
them benefiting other people and that
other people are able to generate income
stress around them and preferably using
local production and local craft
methodologies so I'm also looking at
providing an alternative to the mass
production kind of habits and behaviors
that we're already exhibiting it's not
to say that we wouldn't necessarily use
as production methods as they as they
stand sometimes they are of benefit
everything has its is context but to
create opportunities for craftspeople
and an artisans and because although the
products in question are also designed
to reduce our damage to the environment
and and and create further opportunities
so I can I can give you an example of
that this is this is going to make less
which is why sometimes it's difficult in
this in this narrative but a couple of
years ago I did a product called the the
beta book which is a portable whiteboard
and so it folds up like a notebook and
then inside it you've got a whiteboard
so this is a open-source version which
which anybody can actually produce and
so this is this is one example product
this is mommy folding paper techniques
and things that anybody can buy in any
craft store so it's not that everybody
would necessarily just because you can't
produce your own doesn't mean that
everybody should produce arraign a lot
of people still want to consume but then
there's opportunities for artisans or
people to produce that product likewise
the the the game again just because
people can produce it themselves doesn't
mean they're necessarily going to want
to produce it themselves so again
there's an opportunity there for the
people to produce their own versions of
the game and distribute the game and
profit from the distribution of the game
and so this is one of the the kind of
challenges and opportunities shall we
say in how to give these give these
products away that other people can
produce them other people can benefit
from them perhaps under a common brand
so I would imagine them coming together
under a common website and there may
need to be a separation between projects
in order to allow this to happen so this
is where things get a bit muddy so we
get clarity and then I get muddy again
so apologies for that it's one of the
issues that I that I face as I discover
things all of the time that can be a
benefit to other people and but the the
market is largely geared towards mass
production so I'm looking for
alternative ways and alternative systems
to actually bring these ideas to market
that local makers can benefit from
producing them local craftsmen and
benefit from producing them and and and
people can still access them easily
because no just because you can make it
doesn't mean you want to right and these
products is the I is the idea that they
would sort of be different iterations of
something that you would make with the
the prototyping game you showed like if
for example you make some sort of a
geodesic dome that I don't know he's
good for bees or something you make a
kit around that and then that's what's
sold that that would be that would be
one that would be one branching and one
path I guess right this is this is
always the issue is sometimes sometimes
the game may lead to two to a large
product so yeah so you've got so the
list a few the the game then once we
have the game once we have the the
geodesic yet and then as a larger scale
product that could be produced it's kind
of related to the game but it's a
different set of tools and techniques in
order to produce it this is a kid's toy
was designed in the game it's just a
kind of bird made from recycled plastic
bottles that flaps its wings when you
when you pull the string not really
useful much other than entertaining the
kids and something for shadowplay you
can also get some very interest in
shadow puppetry and various other things
but each each of these things is its own
branch and whilst the the game may be
how I arrived at them and how I come to
design and they each actually come with
their own skill sets for their
individual production okay
so it sounds a bit like there's at least
two levels where one would just sort of
be like giving somebody a big bucket of
leggo that you could build a trillion
things out of and then the next level
those kids versus here here's a
spaceship there's 80 pieces that build a
spaceship it's specifically for that
purpose yeah wondering whether you're a
catalogue of products like all of the
the things that you have made and want
to be available people to make
themselves or for local people to make
themself for their own profit do you
want them to stay separate and in their
own catalogue on their own website their
own you know stores or do you want them
intermingled with other people's
products and other people's like I'm
thinking of like a 3d library that's not
a you know it's not a 3d printing
library but something that's like hey
you can build this yourself and team up
with other people so you can bulk buy
the products and and you know have a DIY
workshop where you're all building
foldable whiteboards together right
here's the material here's that no I
would I would love to I mean my
intention is really once the once once
the system is working I want this to be
something that other inventors and can
also share their ideas through but also
that others can actually build upon the
ideas that everybody contributes and
puts into the the common product pool so
to speak so to take the whiteboard for
example as a case in point there's that
there's a whole load of very easy design
hacks that can be made simply by
printing different artworks by different
designers and then folding those pages
so that's an easy adaptation other
people can build upon also the inside
layers can be replaced and switched out
so you can add anything from drawings
that kids can can draw and color and and
then color again through to business
canvasses and SWOT analysis where that's
kind of old school but you know like
business padding canvas sustainability
canvas different processes that could
appeal to an entire
a different market and an entirely
different market niche so the the idea
really I would like to see is that
that's a space where other people can
can build on and can can adapt and share
their adaptations and share their
designs and also be rewarded for and
derive a benefit for putting those ideas
out into those spaces where where they
should need it and because there's
there's a lot of I don't think I'm alone
in this in this in this challenge I
there are other inventors and other
entrepreneurs out there that I think
suffer continuously from this because of
the the systems of investment and the
the means of reaching the market
essentially mean that we have to and
present ideas in a way that's viable
only to commercial interests and then it
needs to be at a sufficient scale to be
worth we invest are taking the risk and
an inventor isn't or the entrepreneur
isn't rich to to begin with then the
investor takes a punt that the investor
wins because they spread their bear but
the entrepreneur or the inventor they
put their sweat and their time into
creating the idea to discovering the
idea and and ultimately they don't
necessarily have a stake so it kind of
requires an insanity of some form to
actually go down this path I mean I I
went down this path because I was young
and naive but because I've fallen so far
out the system I can't get back and but
when I've worked with entrepreneurs and
inventors in places like Egypt and Sri
Lanka their families are constantly
pulling them towards more stable jobs
and more stable civil service positions
and to be quite honest they're right to
do so because there's no social safety
net for them and their families are also
dependent on their
future and it's not just the
entrepreneur or the inventor that's at
risk if they up excuse my language
but it's some creating an opportunity
space for people that have ideas and
that are looking into things especially
like sustainability where we do need
alternative solutions we do need to
discover and find the alternatives and
bring them to market but I don't think
the existing market model is going to be
sufficient in order to bring about all
of the changes that we need to discover
does that make sense yeah that sounds
really similar to what
Jubilees been suggesting and what I'm
working with honor and this together
tact now ours was specifically focused
for tech but we're hitting those same
issues where the pooling resources for
marketing and that's an interesting idea
and I think we've also discussed pulling
resources for distributing the risk like
you suggested so those are all great
ideas I did want to dive back more into
this into your specific situation and
throw some ideas out that you may have
already considered and discarded for one
reason or another do you mind if I throw
some ideas out so I the the thing seems
like in your kind of priority list I
would say your most important thing that
you want to accomplish is to get the
information out there and get it
popularized as we was saying or make it
more common and accessible because like
you said you're not interested in
necessarily making money as a craftsman
I mean that's part of it but I think
your larger goal of getting it out to
the world is your primary one if I was
in that situation one thing I would
probably consider is is to have a you
website and a YouTube channel where
you're just creating videos on how to do
all the stuff and building up that that
content now that doesn't get you
anywhere to that yeah that might be like
the FIR
generation and maybe even having a
patreon for people that or some other
funding models where people can donate
for supporting your cause and and to
give you the recent I'm and money to
make that content either video or also
just written content on a website and
then we can we can discuss the deeper
steps but have you considered that yet
already yeah that we were going to have
this chat as an opportunity to start to
collect the information together into
into a website so I can actually
articulate and make the ideas accessible
more clearly so I've started playing
about with web slow today and kind of
activating some very very fast old
skills long ago forgotten and I've begun
I think definitely something then
patreon is also something that I've I've
considered so it's this I think is the
one of the declare next steps for me is
to get the website done get up what I've
already done over the last year in this
in in this framework one that one of the
things I'm not sure about still is
whether the the overall the overarching
narrative fits all of the products that
are being created so this is something
that I still need to kind of explore is
it's always having these clear threads
but I I think that's definitely one
channel that needs to be explored I
think with YouTube one of the things I
want to ensure though is that there's
there's some feedback loop that actually
ensures that people don't just what
and then go oh that's nice and share it
but there's to create a feedback loop
where they're also motivated to recreate
it and and then share evidence that they
actually made it in the in in the real
world so I've been exploring like game
dynamics with respect to that
relationship that it's kind of working
out these incentives that people
actually want to copy it because you can
often get in this space of illusion of
people share stuff and then there you go
that's nice and then they share it on
Facebook that's the action they take I
mean if you had if you had one out of
every person that sees it created it
yeah if you have 99 people sharing it
you're gonna reach those 1% to do do it
sooner so I don't I don't think at
anytime you'd want to say I don't want
to have the the shares for the people
that don't use it but yes sending any
way that you can you can phrase it or
encourage the actual participation of it
and if you have a website and a YouTube
channel and you simply say hey make one
send me a video clip and I'll do a
compilation video or I'll give you video
feedback on your thon I think that's a
great incentive for people to or to show
your ideas you know for me I don't know
exactly how the Instagram works so I
can't speak if this could be done on
Instagram but like on Facebook having a
Facebook group or you have the YouTube
videos and then other people can post
their video or their photo of what they
created within that and so it becomes a
community of people who are trying these
things right trying the iteration it's
part of like that's a piece of doing it
right even if you wouldn't make the bird
on a stick because you don't have a kid
for it to do they might make it for
being part of that community right and
having one a month for one a week
whatever your capacity is so that that
is the one people or
xenon and then people can always hear I
mean they come in a month late and they
make the bird one and it's a month ago
they can still post it and have people
comment yep a lot of trainers on on
YouTube like 3d modeling they'll have
weekly contests and so and you don't
even have to actually give anything you
just say oh I like this one the best
right that's basically of like yeah you
like my channel now you're on it yeah
but yeah so have a lot of people create
you know so you could have a design
challenge here's a problem that people
are having providing shade how would you
use these tools to do that or another
week saying you know let's let's all
make this one shape and who can decorate
it the best all right because you want
because you want these dolls would be
aesthetically pleasing just little
competitions like that I think would be
a lot of fun yeah a time-based
one of the things we've been exploring
quite a lot with the the game shadow
play so you cannot transform the the
entire inside space actually by taking
these geometries and then shining
shining light freedom and you can then
actually see the the structures on the
walls of the room around you and make
your own shadow puppets so for example
that was what the bird was about so if
it's if it's like a weekly story and
there's challenges connected to that
weekly story and then people are invited
to create different characters or
archetypes or different structures and
parts of the overall storytelling like
scenes then as the incentive to get
there seen in this in the story and so
maybe that's a way of going about it
like I think not good yeah I could
actually fit quite nicely seems a bit
like between the YouTube
you know content they're talking about a
lot of it is based around just like
emphasizing the final thing that gets
built in sort of you know talking about
the different options there is there any
desire to
I guess build a library of ideas and
sort of a community around the
individual components like hey I used
beeswax and sticks if you don't have
something similar or you know that's
harder to get in your area crowd
sourcing alternatives and having that as
one of the things to talk about like
what other things can use a joining
material or structure or yeah I think
that's also another another factor of
like I guess the the the the the
community of practice and the community
of modeling because it's the same with
the with what I have with the
large-scale structures when I when I
went to London is suddenly I'm in a
place where palm sticks are not lying
around on the street everywhere and I
can't find branches so then I'm having
to use the cardboard and adapt to the
local context in order to solve the
challenges so I think there's there's
definitely some strong in-game
opportunities there actually in in in
having these weekly time-based
challenges having a community feedback
system using the using the video and how
did you produce yours where you are I I
think that's that's actually got some
really strong opportunities and it's a
lot of what the what the game element is
is is about so the the individual game
is called context craft so it's all
about like responding and reacting to
your to your context using what's around
you and and building on that so I think
that could actually be a very very
strong idea yeah I just wanted to
mention because it keeps coming up in my
head there's a reddit stuff whatever
those things called subreddit called DIY
I think that rules are quite sure
that you have to have like made it
yourself it has to be an original
project and yeah I think you have to
even much give instructions on how to
make it yourself somewhere but it's it's
like a milly like there's a ton of
people following it and so getting a
video of like having your YouTube
channel it's hard to get subscribers on
YouTube channel yet even on a subreddit
like that where it's it's basically
automatic and then that's funneling
through to the Facebook or whatever you
have the actual community on right of
people submitting videos and pictures
because YouTube is not the best place
for that it kind of actually filters out
people submitting video and pictures so
yeah like happy not all all feed feed
together finding that the reddit's that
are and pinterest really sensual part of
it is is always finding finding the
right terms and the right places in
which to in which to share is always a
major aspect of the the challenge and
also just finding the right words and
phrases which is yeah I could it's
covered so yeah yeah and you'd asked
about whether all your products fit
under the same kind of website or
identity all right
my the rule I'm starting and you may
have found this also but the rule was
trying to do with all my projects is
keep them all under one in one place
until they're so big that you have to
pull them out because otherwise you just
spend all your time buying domain names
about 60 and building websites that
didn't crash and stuff like that it's
very distracting so yeah you can if if
your site kind of name and I think the
name that you've given is broad enough
that everything should fit under that in
some way or another because then does
they they are tied together by that
common goal and then you could always
break them out later it's not I don't
think it's that hard to break it out and
then you know having a marketplace and
library of how to build these sort of
things and even to
fools like you know maybe I want to
build a geodesic dome and I could go
there and pull up a plan for the size
that I want and then plug in where I'm
at and it would determine from content
created by other users in the area what
materials I could find in the local area
what the cost of any of the parts that I
have to buy or places I could get the
recycled materials I think that would be
an interesting tool and then have people
be able to present designs and maybe
contribute back and modify existing
designs kind of like github if you know
programming and then the ability to you
know pay the designers for the work that
they did and maybe even find other
people in the community craftsmen and
the community I'd put it together for
you if if you don't have the time to do
that that would be a really interesting
kind of future State
I wouldn't even start on any of that
until I would do that getting the
information out there start cataloging
it and stuff but but that would be an
interesting future one of the other
things it's very community building that
it was just coming up was you had talked
about people being engineers and their
parent you know their their families
drawing them out to other more
profitable careers and I think there's a
lot of ingenuity especially in the
developing world where you can live off
of $500 a month right really well pretty
well and finding a way to like if you're
okay in your space right like if you
have your needs met finding a way where
when you bring in money like let's say
there's a scholarship fund where people
are picking the top engineers the top
designers in you know one per country or
one end like actually paid for them to
do this full-time right like hey family
look what I'm doing and I'm getting paid
to do it and getting that prestige and
it's bringing a global community
together in a way that's showcasing them
right and having a new person hey this
is the thing we're making this week
they're gonna show you how to do this
month and we're gonna you know like
bringing that was just okay thing to add
on so they can work on yeah yeah
what okay to build on what Bentley was
saying I think I'm like one of the
earliest things that you could have the
community sort of generate and possibly
sell would just be the building
materials if I live in an area that has
a bunch of plastic pollution and I feel
so inclined to make you know some
structure or joining or whatever the
bits and pieces are having like the
opposite of Amazon where it's you know
people going out to their area saying
hey anybody who lives with an X distance
from me
show me people who are you know are
building these materials nearby because
maybe I'm not that interested in that
part of it I just want to be able to
build with my kids or even just collect
in right yeah so you have the
instructions on YouTube and stuff how to
do it but if you don't wanted to do that
I think that might be one of the easiest
things because then that lets people at
all stages from the learning how to do
it and just try not to tinker the people
who want to build full domes yeah don't
forget to build the materials and then
people who want to build kits could
either do it themselves
or just buy the pieces from there and
sort of have your own almost like a
supply chain in the system yeah exactly
I think that's the that's a big big
opportunity like once you get into the
to the to the ecosystem is that people
need like if people want to own the
thing then that creates a need or a
market for the thing and then I'm body
else can okay I can take up the
challenge to to produce it and and
profit from the production of it or I
can go and source the materials from the
from the sourcing of the materials and
allurements benefiting assists getting
the trash extracted from it and and and
so on and so forth it's I think it's got
some strong kind of only win kind of
infinite win opportunities within that
within that space so it's going to be
interesting to see how it
and we've also got an app that we're
working on to to develop whereby
actually it's easier to scan the the
three-dimensional designs and understand
how to produce them because this is a
separate challenge that we're working on
as you can see it's really hard actually
to understand what this is a video even
because some free geometry doesn't
really translate over a to dinah
two-dimensional space so we're also work
on how to develop that in augmented
reality and ultimately how people will
be able to view in physical space what
these objects would look like and then
find out to produce exactly so to break
down the number of parts number of bits
and all of these different elements but
this is a long long long game and plant
small seeds and grow it step by step and
little by little
Yui arrows over here it will yeah and I
do 3d modeling and web design so putting
3d models on a on a web page that you
can just kind of like spin without
having any plugins or anything or
definitely doable these days because
it's easier to visualize if you can kind
of like drag it around a bit
but yeah but I think you can also do it
in video I mean once you kind of get
used to recording yourself and just
taking the camera and you know rotating
it around so that they can get a feel
for the 3d and then you know get two
cameras and the stereoscopic ones know
if they have it on their their phone
they could or the you know the the 3d
that's really coming into coming into
more common technologies and so that'll
be good yeah yeah I'll maybe need to
design a 3d rotating table next us I
just wanted to ask
jae-won out of what we've been talking
about draws you in the most like what is
it you want to spend your time doing and
if you could find a like perfect partner
in this
what skills would they have or what
would they do that you don't want to do
or can't do good good question I think
from from from my perspective and it's a
little bit of a challenge given where
I'm where where I'm located but my body
that was taking the the the ideas that
I'm generating and putting them in a way
that people can relate to online
organizing the organizing the content
and making it accessible for people that
that it's easy to have that digital
translation and and documentation
process and this is this is sometimes
the the hard part I guess for me and I
think it's a hard part for a lot of
makers is the the actual documentation
the actual putting getting the the the
products nicely photographed put online
step by step and and packaging it in a
way that's easy for for people to relate
to and and replicate and I think part of
that also is that the the act of
replication actually requires to some
degree a slightly different mindset to
the active to the active discovery and
it's it's it's a slightly different
relationship you know it's the eyes that
seeing from the other perspective and
attempting to copy well often because
I don't want to sound big-headed but I
am quite materially literate and because
of that sometimes I take for granted
things that are very simple for me to do
but for people that don't have that
experience yet are surprisingly
difficult and I've often been surprised
by basic stuff like handling a pair of
scissors and that I expect people to be
able to just kind of pick up a plastic
bottle and cut it but actually often
people struggle with even these
rudimentary things and because they they
they haven't had that that material
experienced one quick suggestion on that
if you're doing the YouTube videos maybe
you can invite someone who you know is
very low
literate on materials and you walk them
through the project and then they get to
be the audience and the core asking the
questions the audience would ask it is
very hard when you're learning to teach
to think from the mind of someone who
doesn't know the curse of knowledge yeah
we are coming up close to the hour so if
you want to do any closing statements
search closing J and then I just want to
know from you how this process went and
any suggestions you have for us doing
project raisings for you in the future
or anybody else in the future okay that
was really telling the the opportunity
actually to share what I'm up to and and
check my ability to UK which was my main
kind of party and I really yeah very
grateful for the and for the opportunity
and the the feedback I think has been
really useful ideas come out of it
especially like this kind of event led
process I think that could actually be a
really useful aspect of the the thinking
around the game that I've been trying
to develop is especially addressing a
challenge of how to get remote
participation and I think that's been
that has been really useful going
forward so I really appreciate that
so no I think it's it's it's it's been
very useful and very rewarding I
appreciate it thank you very much thank
you it's been an hour and trying to keep
my stream yards to an hour to keep it
within my monthly allotment so we can
say goodbye to YouTube and less Adriel
or Bentley or J have anything else they
would like to say before before that no
good all right bye YouTube see you next
week for our next project raising